Guide to the Semen and Pavel Iushkevich Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Semen and Pavel I︠U︡shkevich papers
1892-1985
1892-1930
GEN MSS 290
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.2
(4 boxes)
Writings and correspondence by or relating to the I︠U︡shkevich brothers and their family. Includes family photographs, and corrected typescripts of stories, plays and screenplays in Russian and in translation.
I︠U︡shkevich, Semen, 1868-1927
I︠U︡shkevich, P. S. (Pavel Solomonovich), 1873-1945
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from Nina IUshkevich and Adolf Pavolvich IUshkevich, 1988-1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile material in box 4 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
SEMEN SOLOMONOVICH IUSHKEVICH (1868-1927) & PAVEL SOLOMONOVICH IUSHKEVICH (1873-1945)
Semen IUshkevich was born in Odessa in 1868, educated in the Jewish schools of the city and studied pharmacy at the University of St. Vladimir in Kiev and medicine in Paris. He began writing in the late 1890s, focusing on realistic depictions of middle-class Jewish life in Russia. He was an early contributor to Znanie, but later turned to playwriting. Sometime between 1917 and 1920, he emigrated with his family, finally settling in Paris. He continued writing plays, novels, and film scripts until his death in 1927.
Pavel IUshkevich was born in Odessa on June 29 (July 11), 1873. While he concentrated in his studies in mathematics, he was active in Marxist political groups. He later studied at the Faculty of Sciences of the Sorbonne and the University of St. Petersburg, eventually working as a journalist, editor, translator, though eventually disdaining politics. An expanded account of his life can be found in the biographical notes in folder 57-59.
Scope and Contents
The Semen and Pavel IUshkevich Papers contain writings and correspondence by or relating to the IUshkevich brothers and their family as well as family photographs, and corrected typescripts of stories, plays and screenplays in Russian and in translation.
Jewish authors; Russian drama -- 20th Century; Russian literature -- 20th Century; Russia -- Emigration and immigration; I︠U︡shkevich, P. S. (Pavel Solomonovich), 1873-1945; I︠U︡shkevich, Semen, 1868-1927; I︠U︡shkevich family
- Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich Papers, 1903-1985; Series I; 0.41; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich Papers is organized in three subseries. Each is arranged alphabetically.
  - WRITINGS
    - "L'amour enchanté": typescript carbon signed, with holograph addition, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Les Cinq Jules": typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Demony nashei zhizni"
      - Typescript carbon, 1925 Jun 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - French translation: typescript carbon, 1925 Jun 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Devushka v krasnom"
      - Typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "Maiden in Purple" (English language translation: typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Epizody: partial English translation, corrected typescript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Evrei": synopsis in English by Catherine Routsky, corrected typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Golod, v gorode, otche nash ... (printed version), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes pieces of three separate books: Golod, Otche nash, Chetrye apostola, Zhalost, Tri kladbishcha, Novyi prorok, Gubernantka, V Avgustovskii vecher.
    - "Ishchet Rossiiu": holograph in unidentified hand (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Nashi sestry. Printed version, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Pages 239-246 wanting.
    - "Povest' o gospodine Son'kine"
      - Yiddish translation, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - English synopsis, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Prestuplenie Mastera Birta": typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - V' lavochke. Printed, fragment, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Pages 34-37
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - "Bycher": spóldzielnia z ogr. odp: TLS, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Chulock, G.: ALS, 1925 Jul 11 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Comédie des Champs-Élysées: TLS, 1925 Jul 11 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Signed Louis Jouvet
    - Max Pfeffer: 2 TLS, with TL of Iushkevich's reply, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Società Italiana degli Autori: printed invitation, 1925 Feb 28 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Société des auteurs de films: 2 TLS with deposit receipts, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Zwiazek literatów i dziennikarzy zydowskich w Warszawie: TLS, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Aleksandr Bakhrakh, "Ob avtore Leona Dreia: in entire printed issue of Novoe russkoe Slovo, 1985 Aug 18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Ciné France Film: contract for "Les cinq Jules", typescript, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Postal receipts, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Power of Attorney: TL, 1926 Mar 12 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Pavel Solomonovich IUshkevich Papers, 1896-1988; Series II; 0.2; (1 box)
  Series II, Pavel Solomonovich IUshkevich Papers are organized in two subseries. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically. The diaries in Other Papers are arranged chronologically, followed by biographical notes.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Derment, V., 1900 Oct 31 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Entsiklopedicheski slovar' (Brokgauz i Efron), 1913 Jul 12 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - IUshkevich, Semen S., 1917 Sep 7 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Includes: Commentary by A. P. Iush- kevich, dated Dec. 3, 1989
    - Ivanchin-Pisarev, Aleksandr Ivanovich, 1896 Jun 23 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Izdatel'stvo "Shipovnik", 1910 Nov 11 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Kovalevsky, M., 1898 Dec 10 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich: photostat, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Lunacharsky, Anatoly Vasilievich, 1909, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Mikhailovskii, N.K. (Nikolai Konstantinovich), 1897-99 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Muizhel', V.V. (Viktor Vasil'evich), 1909 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Nestorov, S, 1910 Nov (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Novaia Zhezn', 1910 Oct, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Novyi Zhurnal Dlia'vsiekh, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Obrazovanie, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
      With a document.
    - Obshchestvo nuzhdaishchim literateraa, 1913 Jan 18 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Osvobozhdenie: TLS, 1910 Nov 19 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Ovsianiko-Kulikovskii, D.N. (Dimitrii Nikolaevich), 1911-12 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Prometej, 1909-11 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Russkoe Bogatstvo, 1896 Jul 7 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Shapovinsky, D., 1896 Feb 7 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Tsederbaum, V., 1916 Jun 22 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Veresaev, V.V. (Vikenti Vikent'evich), 1909 Mar 4 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Vestnik Evropy, 1910-11 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - "Zhizn", 1900 Nov 3 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Diaries, 1909-20 (Box 2, Folder 51-56)
      Numbered 1-6
    - Biographical notes on Pavel Solomonovich IUshkevich, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 57-59)
      Includes: Photocopy of holograph ms biographical sketch by A. P. IUshkevich, in Russian, a typescript of the same, and typescript of an English language translation.
- IUshkevich Family Papers, ca. 1880-1926; Series III; 0.4; (1 box)
  Series III, IUshkevich Family Papers, are organized in two subseries, which are arranged alphabetically.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - IUshkevich, Anna Grigorievna, to
      - IUshkevich, Liza Solomonova, ca. 1916 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - IUshkevich, Semen Solomonovich, ca. 1900-17 (Box 3, Folder 61-62)
    - IUshkevich, Pavel Solomonovich, to
      - IUshkevich, Liza Solomonova, 1929 Aug 23 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - IUshkevich, Solomon Moiseevich, to
      - IUshkevich, Mikhail, Semen and Liza, ca. 1895 (Box 3, Folder 64)
      - IUshkevich, Semen Solomonovich, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Portraits of Individuals
      - IUshkevich, Anastasiia, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 66)
      - IUshkevich, Anna Grigorievna, ca. 1917 (Box 3, Folder 67)
      - IUshkevich, Mikhail Solomonovich, ca. 1880-90 (Box 3, Folder 68)
        Brother of the writer in uniform.
      - IUshkevich, Natal'ia Semenovna, 1918-19, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 69)
      - IUshkevich, Nina Semenovna, 1923-25, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 70)
      - IUshkevich, Pol' Semenovich, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 71)
        Son of Polina Finkel'shteyn, the writer's first wife.
      - IUshkevich, Semen Solomonovich, 1892-1926 (Box 3, Folder 72-73)
        Includes photographs during the period of the author's enrollment at the Ecole de Médecine; a portrait taken at the Theatre named for K. Nezlobina, at the time when Chelovek vozdukha (Luftmensch) was being performed, and a portrait at the Izmailov dacha, where the writer spent many summers, Bol'shoi Fontan, Odessa.
      - IUshkevich, Solomon Moiseevich, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 74)
      - Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich's grave, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Group Portraits
      - Anastasiia IUshkevich and Natal'ia Semenova IUshkevich, 1901 Dec 16 (Box 3, Folder 76)
      - Anastasiia Solomonovna, Natal'ia and Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich, ca. 1905 (Box 3, Folder 77)
      - Anastasiia, Natasha and Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich. (Box 3, Folder 78)
      - Anastasiia Solomonovna Zeilinger and Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich, wedding portrait, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 79)
      - Anastasiia, Nina Semenova and Semen Solomonovich IUshevich., 1917, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 80)
      - Anastasiia, Nina, Natal'ia and Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich: passport photo, 1920 Jan 16 (Box 3, Folder 81)
      - Mikhail Solomonovich and Sofiia IUshkevich (Box 3, Folder 82)
      - Natal'ia and Nina Semenova IUshkevich (Box 3, Folder 83)
      - Natal'ia, Nina and Sophia IUshkevich. (Box 3, Folder 84)
      - Natasha, Nina and Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich (Box 3, Folder 85)
      - Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich and Chaim Nachman Bialik, Sep 1917 (Box 3, Folder 86)
        [Bialik was a renowned Hebrew renaissance poet, during this time IUshkevich and Bialik had been working on a Sbornik .]
      - Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich and Nina, ca. 1917 (Box 3, Folder 87)
      - Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich and Nina, ca. 1917 (Box 3, Folder 88)
      - Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich with family, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 89)
      - Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich and unidentified actress, ca. 1910 (Box 3, Folder 90)
        Includes photo of letter.
      - Znanie writers: Evgeny N. Chirikov, Semen Solomonovich IUshkevich, and S. Naidenov [pseud.], ca. 1903 (Box 3, Folder 91)
      - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 92)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.2; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 4: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 1 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Box 1, folder 2 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Box 1, folder 3 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Box 1, folder 6 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Box 1, folder 9 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Box 1, folder 15 (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Box 1, folder 19 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Box 1, folder 24 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Box 1, folder 41 (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - Box 3, folder 60 (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Box 3, folder 61 (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Box 3, folder 62 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Box 3, folder 63 (Box 4, Folder 105)
  - Box 3, folder 64 (Box 4, Folder 106)